Finding Aid for the Doris Lyons Hoover Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Doris Lyons Hoover Papers
multiple
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0761
2.1 linear_feet
Biographical Note
Doris M. Lyons was born in 1928 in Fort Payne, Alabama to Wilburn and Marion Lyons. She grew up in Chattanooga, Tennessee and attended the University of Tennessee, Chattanooga, graduating with an art (painting) degree in the late 1940s. She married Jack L. Hoover in 1949, moved to California in 1952, and they have three daughters.
Doris Lyons Hoover is a retired textile/fabric artist, writer, and teacher. She is especially known for her quilts, tassels, and potholders. She is the author and illustrator of “Too Hot to Handle: Potholders and How to Make Them” (1993), and co-author of “Tassels” (1978). She also taught a variety of classes including creativity seminars and fiber arts workshops. In the 1960s she co-founded the Peninsula Stitchery Guild and later served as its president.
Scope and Content Note
The papers are contained in five Hollinger boxes and measures 1.66 linear feet. They are comprised of personal correspondence, newspaper clippings and articles about Doris Hoover, a CD of hundreds of photos of her creative works, as well as copies of the books she wrote. Her personal correspondence includes letters and postcards from other well-known artists such as Bets Ramsey and Jean Ray Laury. Bets Ramsey is an award-winning quilter, lecturer, and author. She was the founder and director of the Southern Quilt Symposium and curated major annual quilt exhibits for many (17) years. Jean Ray Laury was an influential early modern American quiltmaker, freelance designer, lecturer, and author of several books. Of special interest are the Hoover family Christmas cards, dating from the 1950s through the 1980s, all designed by Doris.
- Correspondence – Incoming
  - Iris Bell, January 6, 1984 - March 5, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Iris Bell, April 14, 1985 -August 15, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Iris Bell, February 12, 1986 - February 17, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Iris Bell, December 19, 1986 - May 30, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Iris Bell, October 18, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Iris Bell, November 1, 1989 - January ?, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Iris Bell, March 30, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Iris Bell, November 26, 1990 - December 16, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Iris Bell, January, 1993- December 27, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Iris Bell, January 9, 1995 - December 18, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Iris Bell, January 19, 1998 - January 3, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Iris Bell, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Iris Bell, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Iris Bell, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Iris Bell, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Iris Bell, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Iris Bell, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Iris Bell, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Iris Bell, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Iris Bell, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Iris Bell, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Iris Bell, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Iris Bell, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Iris Bell, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Correspondence – Incoming
  - Phyllis Dukes, February 17, 1973 - December 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Phyllis Dukes, January 16, 1974 - December 4, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Phyllis Dukes, February 7, 1975 - April 27, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Phyllis Dukes, May 8, 1975 - November 19, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Phyllis Dukes, January 16, 1976 - August 3, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Phyllis Dukes, January 19, 1978 - December 9, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Phyllis Dukes, March 5, 1979 - January 29, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Phyllis Dukes, June 10, 1981 – April 17, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Phyllis Dukes, January 9, 1993 - July 7, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Phyllis Dukes, August 14, 1995 - October 27, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Phyllis Dukes, April 27, 1988 - January 24, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Phyllis Dukes, February 28, 1991 - October 27, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Phyllis Dukes, November 13, 1993 - April 17, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Phyllis Dukes, January 29, 1996 - April 18, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Phyllis Dukes, June 22, 1997 - May 8, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Phyllis Dukes, January 7, 2000 - February 24, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Phyllis Dukes, September 2, 2000 - May 14, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Phyllis Dukes, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Marilyn Green, November 29, 1990 - February 17, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Marilyn Green, July 12, 1995 - October 28, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Marilyn Green, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Vickie Johnson, September 21, 1990 - May 13, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Gerry Kehm, August 1, 1979 - February 10, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Gerry Kehm, March 23, 1982 - August 22, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Gerry Kehm, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Jean Ray Laury, September 21, 1972 - July 1, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Jean Ray Laury, September 27, 1977 - December 12, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Jean Ray Laury, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Jean Ray Laury, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Jean Ray Laury, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Jean Ray Laury, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Correspondence – Incoming
  - Jane McElroy, June 27, 1980 - November 4, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Jane McElroy, October 23, 1986 - December 28, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Jane McElroy, January 20, 1987 - December 28, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Jane McElroy, January 27, 1988 - September 28, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Jane McElroy, March 6, 1991 - October 18, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Jane McElroy, February 10, 1994 - December 18, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Jane McElroy, October 21, 1997 - June 20, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Jane McElroy, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, February 21, 1976 - September 25, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, October, 8, 1987 - November 6, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous, March 6, 1995 - July 5, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, July 16, 1995 - November 28, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, February 15, 1996 - January 14, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, February 6, 1997 - November 2, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, January 4, 1998 - July 30, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, August 10, 1999 - December 27, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, February 10, 2000 - July 10, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Correspondence – Incoming
  - Bets Ramsey, July 7, 1973 - December 23, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bets Ramsey, January 8, 1991 - December 31, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bets Ramsey, January 5, 1992 - December 28, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Bets Ramsey, January 4, 1993 - May 27, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Bets Ramsey, June 16, 1993 - December 1, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Bets Ramsey, January 6, 1994 - June 14, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Bets Ramsey, July 5, 1994 - November 30, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Bets Ramsey, January 9, 1995 - June 4, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Bets Ramsey, July 8, 1995 - December 28, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Bets Ramsey, February 5, 1996 - August 14, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Bets Ramsey, September 18, 1996 - March 6, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Bets Ramsey, April 26, 1997 - December 28, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Bets Ramsey, January 5, 1998 - December 26, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Bets Ramsey, February 8, 1999 - July 11, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Bets Ramsey, October 1, 2000 - June 1, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Bets Ramsey, January 5, 2002 - December 3, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Bets Ramsey, January 2, 2003 - December 29, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Bets Ramsey, May 15, 2004 - March 30, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Bets Ramsey, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Beryl Self, May 31, 1986 - June 8, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Beryl Self, September 10, 1990 - September 27, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Beryl Self, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Writings, Photographs and Creations
  - Articles About Doris Hoover (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Article by Doris Hoover (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence Re: Ideas for Religious Textiles Book (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Fabric Art CD (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Fabric Art Photos/Negatives (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Workshop Photos (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Museum Exhibits (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Publications (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Richmond Art Center Exhibit (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - UT Chattanooga Quilt Exhibit (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Hoover Family Christmas Cards – created by Doris, early 1950s (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Hoover Family Christmas Cards – created by Doris, 1955 - 1958 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Hoover Family Christmas Cards – created by Doris, 1959 - 1962 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Hoover Family Christmas Cards – created by Doris, 1963 - 1966 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Hoover Family Christmas Cards – created by Doris, 1967 - 1970 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Hoover Family Christmas Cards – created by Doris, 1971 - 1974 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Hoover Family Christmas Cards – created by Doris, 1975, 1977 - 1979 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Hoover Family Christmas Cards – created by Doris, 1981 - 1984 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Hoover Family Christmas Cards – created by Doris, 1985 – 1987 - 1989 (Box 5, Folder 20)